Network segmentation is the act of physically
and/or logically breaking up a network into
smaller networks.
Why break up a network?
Physical location plays a role in this as,
in a multi-building campus, for example, it
makes sense to have a local network in each
physical building.
There are situations in which, though, in
a single building, you may want to break up
a network logically.
Take, for example, a computer training center
that has two classrooms, an administrative
staff, and a repair shop in the back of the
building.
Does it make sense to have everyone on the
same network?
One very important aspect to think through
here is that of permissions.
Do we want classroom students seeing what
is going on over on the administrative side
of the building?
Probably not.
And the repair shop takes malware off devices.
We definitely want that area to be isolated.
Right there, that's three logical networks
we would want: one for the classrooms, one
for the administrative staff, and one for
the repair shop.
Again, if you think one group should be isolated
from others, that defines a network segment.
And, as covered elsewhere in this course,
a physical network can easily be broken up
into multiple VLANs to create multiple logical
networks.